NPR has
Speaker 1: launched a new team called Code Switch, covering race, ethnicity, and culture. That name refers to the practice of code switching, changing the way we talk when we talk with different kinds of people in different conversations.
Speaker 2: This week, our Code Switch team is exploring the impact of the huge
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): demographic shifts in America. They're focusing on Oakland, California, once a hub of West Coast African-American culture.
In
Speaker 1: the 1940s and 50s, its music scene was dubbed the Harlem of the West.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): In the 60s, the city gave birth to the Black Panther.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Party. And by the 80s, blacks made up nearly half the city's population.
Speaker 1: Today, Oakland is one of the most diverse cities in the United States, but some worry that diversity is diluting its black cultural identity. This is an issue affecting cities across the country like Atlanta, Washington, D.C., and Newark, New Jersey. NPR's Shireen Marisol Maragi has our story.
Ten
Speaker 4: years ago,
Speaker 5: you wouldn't see a trio of mustachioed white guys playing old-timey music and drawing a supportive crowd smack in the middle of Telegraph Avenue in Oakland on a Friday night. I know. I lived here back then.
But
Speaker 5: now, that kind of thing goes down on the first Friday of every month. And that's where we are tonight, walking with hordes of people, eating food truck grub, popping in and out of hip bars and galleries. It's called First Fridays or Art Murmur.
And it
Speaker 5: takes place in a part of Oakland that was once called "Downtown" but after redevelopment is now "Uptown," Oakland's new entertainment district. Chris Riggins performs stand-up comedy at the street festival every month.
Speaker 7: This is very New Oakland. It's New Oakland, but the only issue right now we're having is getting New Oakland to accept Old Oakland.
Speaker 8: You hear that a lot.
Speaker 8: New Oakland versus Old Oakland. Riggins explains.
Speaker 9: When I say Old Oakland, what I mean is really the people that were born and raised here that often get forgotten.
Speaker 10: And that's basically really the black and brown people in Oakland because right now we're having a big gentrification. A lot of people that aren't from Oakland that wouldn't come to Oakland ten years ago are now moving to Oakland.
Speaker 8: And the people from Old Oakland, they're moving out.
Speaker 8: parts of oakland that were affordable
Speaker 5: are being revitalized gentrified people are leaving neighboring san francisco because the rents are crazy high that's pushing oakland's
Speaker 11: rents up but violence is also up the murder rate here jumped 22 last year stand
Speaker 12: where you are stay still and
be ready for
Speaker 12: the moment of silence
Speaker 5: Everything stopped for a moment at this first Friday to honor Keontae Campbell, an 18-year-old student shot and killed last month. Three-quarters of the murder victims in Oakland are Black, like Keontae. Those two factors, higher rents and crime, are triggers for the nearly 25 percent drop in Oakland's Black population over the last two decades.
Speaker 13: That's so funny because I'm one of them.
Speaker 5: Dave Sweets Ward is an Oakland native planning his suburban escape. He doesn't want to raise his daughter around all that shooting. Sweets is like an old Oakland rep now that his dad Sweet Jimmy has passed on.
Speaker 14: Let's say Michael Jackson is the king of pop. Let's just say Sweet Jimmy is the king of the nightlife in Oakland.
Speaker 5: Sweet Jimmy Ward was one of the most successful bar and nightclub owners in Oakland for decades. King of the nightlife until 2006 when he sold jimmies.
Speaker 5: one of Oakland's largest black-owned and operated clubs. He
Speaker 15: owned it. No renting, no leasing, all his. Sweet
Speaker 5: Jimmy came from Louisiana in the mid-50s to work as a longshoreman. Many African-Americans in Oakland have family who moved
Speaker 16: from the south to work in the shipyards.
Longshoreman
Speaker 5: by day, bartender at night. Sweet Jimmy opened his first bar in 1969 on Telegraph Avenue. Back
Speaker 17: then, Jimmy's patrons nodded their afros and nursed cocktails while they listened to blues greats like Bobby Blue Bland.
Speaker 18: They call it stormy-minded But Tuesday's just as bad
And the
Speaker 8: bar's investors were Sweet Jimmy's cousins, Melvin and Huey Newton.
Speaker 19: Huey Newton sprang to national prominence in 1966 as one of the founders of the Black Panther Party in Oakland. Black
Speaker 17: Panthers and the blues. You can't get more old Oakland than that. But when I asked Dave
Speaker 5: Ward what his dad Sweet Jimmy would say about Uptown Oakland in 2013, Ward says...
Speaker 20: he couldn't say nothing, but I guess it's beautiful,
but...
"It ain't for
Speaker 21: black folks."
"Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-Oak-O "Oak, how
Speaker 22: you feeling? You feel good?"
Later, on that same
Speaker 5: Friday night in Uptown, DJ Z Trip rocks the turntables at a club called "The New Parish"
for
Speaker 11: a crowd that looks a lot like New Oakland. White, Latino, Asian, and black, but
a lot
Speaker 24: less black.
Speaker 24: New parish owner
Speaker 17: Michael O'Connor is a San Francisco native with Irish roots.
Speaker 25 (lower-pitched voice): And by saying this is the new parish, it's kind of like a new area of town.
Speaker 5: O'Connor says Sweet Jimmy's
Speaker 17: building was empty for a couple of years before he bought and remodeled it. Old Oakland now houses New Oakland.
Speaker 26: We want to have a successful Oakland. It's got to be diversified.
Speaker 26: but I
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): think that there's still, and hopefully there will be always, a dominant thread going through that fabric of African-American and black culture.
-
Speaker 17: And O'Connor told me Oakland has the potential to maintain its strong, diverse identity. He says it helps that what he calls identity politics are no longer in vogue. -
Speaker 28: We went through a period of time in the '90s, particularly where there was a lot of white guilt. I think that
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): all races,
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): can overanalyze who they are and what they are.
But
Speaker 25 (lower-pitched voice): when you're out having fun at a show at 11 p.m. on a Friday night, those things aren't that relevant. I
spoke with
Speaker 5: Oakland natives born in the 90s who never knew there was a sweet Jimmy, don't know much about Black Panthers
Speaker 29: or the Blues, and don't really think of Oakland as having a Black cultural identity.
Speaker 30: Occasionally, I hang out with a lot of Polly's. Antoinette Allen is a senior. On her high
Speaker 5: school campus, Tongan and Samoan students go by Polly's, SHORT
FOR POLICY.
Speaker 5: recently
i
Speaker 31: started listening to their music and i can tell you i have a few songs on my phone that i just play non-stop she whips out that
Speaker 32: phone and starts searching for one of her favorites i love the song i love the song and
i play
Speaker 33: the song for everybody because like i love this song
Speaker 5: antonette is black listening to r&b sung by pacific islanders raised in oakland the song's video was filmed on international
Speaker 17: boulevard and the vocalists crooned to their love interest in in front of a taco truck
Speaker 17: called Tacos Los Amigos.
Speaker 34: This is Oakland in
Speaker 17: 2013. Some say it's the heart of multicultural America. Others told me
Speaker 11: it's losing its soul. But you get a sense that
Speaker 35: whatever it is, it's changing, fast.
Speaker 35: Shireen Marisol Maragi, NPR News.